Nothing's happening yet.
But notice, the program
is still running.
And so if I move my cursor, move
my cursor, move my cursor, and--
[MEOWING]
OK, so maybe we could add some Waiting.
But the cat does not want
to be pet, in this case.
But it's indeed conditional.
So there we have an
incarnation in Scratch
of doing something conditionally.
Now, we can make this really
cool, really fast, if you will.
Let me stop this version.
Let me go ahead and do this.
Let me go ahead and
throw all of this away.
Let me go into my little
Extensions bucket over here.
And let me do Video Sensing, since
most laptops or phones these days have
cameras.
And there, indeed, I am,
with Sanders behind me.
And let me do this.
When Video Motion-- and
let me get out of the way.
When Video Motion is
Greater Than some value.
So 10 is the default. This is just a
number that measures how much motion
there is or isn't.
So small number is like no motion.
Big number is lots of motion.
So I'm going to choose 50,
somewhat arbitrarily here-- so 50.
This is not normal to
program off to the side.
But I'm now going to say this.
When Video Motion is 50, go ahead
and Play Sound Meow like this.
So the cat is still in that world.
I'm going to stop the
program and rerun it.
So here we go, Green Flag.
And now here comes-- all
right, this is a little creepy,
the way I'm petting the cat, but--
and-- [SIGH]
[MEOWING]
OK.
[LAUGHTER]
There we go.
OK, so 50 was too big of a number.
I have to pet the cat faster.
[MEOWING]
Whereas this, if--
I don't know--
[LAUGHTER]
Yeah, so--
[MEOW]
OK, so you can make things even
more interactive in this way
by just assembling
different puzzle pieces.
And honestly, there are so many
different puzzle pieces in here.
We're not going to even scratch
the surface of a lot of them.
But they generally
just do what they say.
And indeed, when you see on
the screen here this pallet
of puzzle pieces, really a lot of
programming, especially early on,
when learning a language, is just trying
different things and try and fail.
And if it doesn't work quite right,
look for an alternative solution
there too, as even I just
had to do a moment ago.
Well, let's go ahead and use, actually,
how about another example of something
a predecessor of yours made?
Let me go ahead and grab a program
I opened in advance here called
Whack-A-Mole Might we get a
brave volunteer to come up,
who is willing to whack a mole
with their head, virtually?
Maybe-- OK, let's see,
how about in way back?
You want to come on down?
All right, come on down.
Sure, a round of applause
for our volunteer.
[APPLAUSE]
All right, so here we have--
come on down.
AUDIENCE: Hi there.
DAVID J. MALAN: What's your name?
AUDIENCE: I'm Josh.
DAVID J. MALAN: Oh, actually,
say it into the microphone.
AUDIENCE: Hi, I'm Josh.
DAVID J. MALAN: OK, nice.
Welcome, Josh.
Come on over.
[APPLAUSE]
All right, so same idea here--
I'll take the mic back.
You'll have to stand
in front of the camera.
In just a moment, you're going to
have to position your head in a box
that your classmate
from yesteryear created.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
And we'll start with Beginner.
AUDIENCE: OK.
DAVID J. MALAN: So line your
head up in the box in a moment.
AUDIENCE: All right.
[LAUGHTER]
DAVID J. MALAN: Nice.
12 seconds.
5 seconds.
Notice the score's up to 18 already.
Pretty good.
All right, a round of applause
for Josh, if we could.
[APPLAUSE]
So notice how using some
fairly simple primitives,
things do get interesting pretty fast.
And how was that implemented?
Well, there were probably
at least four sprites.
So you're not confined to just one cat.
You can create more and more
sprites, change what they look like.
So they actually look
like a mole, in this case.
There's probably some conditionals
in there, some loops for 30 seconds.
That's checking if Josh's
head's movement is exceeding
some value over this
way or over this way,
then increment something
called a variable.
We'll see those too.
Just like in algebra
you might have x and y
and z, storing values like
numbers, so can computer programs,
have variables called x or y or z,
or more descriptively called Score,
as in this case at top
right, or another variable
called Countdown, typically one
word in code, but in this case
two words, that just store some value.
So there's probably some
math going on in there
whereby the author of this program
just is incrementing, that is,
adding 1 and 1 every time it detected
that a mole had been whacked,
in this case, with movement.
So back in the day, I, myself, actually
implemented my very first program
in Scratch when I was a graduate
student, actually, at MIT--
cross-registered at MIT, taking
a class from MIT's Media Lab,
specifically, the lifelong kindergarten
group, which is the group that created
Scratch, itself.
And the program I wrote all
those years ago and still
rather cling to is a
little something here
called Oscartime, that I thought I'd
play just a quick excerpt of myself
here.
So in this case, consider,
as the music starts playing,
how this program, which is much
more sophisticated, certainly,
than the earliest "Say hello" examples
we just did might also be implemented.
Let me go ahead now and
click the Green Flag.
[MUSIC - OSCAR THE GROUCH, "I LOVE
TRASH"]
OSCAR THE GROUCH:
(SINGING) Oh, I love trash.
DAVID J. MALAN: OK, so some trash is
moving, presumably in some kind of loop
from the top.
If I'm touching the mouse
cursor, it follows me.
If I hover over the
trash can, it responds.
If I let go, in some kind
of loop, Oscar pops out,
creates a variable
with the current score.
And it happens again.
OSCAR THE GROUCH: (SINGING)
It's awful, the holes.
And the laces are torn.
A gift from my mother
the day I was born.
I love it because it's trash.
Oh, I--
DAVID J. MALAN: It's
pretty easy at first but--
OSCAR THE GROUCH: (SINGING)
--anything dirty or dingy--
DAVID J. MALAN: So I don't
need to keep playing this up
on stage in front of everyone.
So my score is already
now up to some 6 or so.
But in a moment, too, you'll
see that it's going to escalate.
So I'm taking into account
some time apparently.
So now--
OSCAR THE GROUCH: (SINGING) I have
here some newspaper, 13 months old.
DAVID J. MALAN: So more and more
sprites are suddenly appearing.
And notice, that each
time they're appearing
from a different part of the screen.
That's an illusion, perhaps, too, that--
pick a random number between x and y.
So you can actually pick
some range of values
to have the game constantly changing.
And indeed, I'm going to
go ahead and click Stop,
since I spent like eight hours
plus, years ago, making this.
And I can never listen
to the song again,
not that I should be anyway
at this point in my life.
But this song is synchronized then with
a lot of the actions that's happening.
And ultimately, there's just
a lot of building blocks.
But I didn't sit down and implement
Oscartime, as I called it, all at once.
I really did take baby
steps, so to speak.
And I figured out, well, how could I
decompose this vision I had at the time
to create this game ultimately?
And how do I bite off maybe
the easiest parts first?
And honestly, the first thing I did was
I found this image, and I just dragged
and dropped it into Scratch--
OK, done-- like, lamppost is installed.
It doesn't do anything.
It's not interactive.
But I at least set the stage,
so to speak, for the program.
Then what else might I have done?
Well, let me do this.
Let me go ahead and open
up in another editor here
an early incarnation of
Oscartime by doing this.
Let me go into Oscartime here.
Let me full screen this.
And here you have--
let me hide the trash
for just a moment--
is what I might call the second
version of my program, wherein,
at the top right of the stage here,
I had the lamppost, which I just
dragged and dropped and got going,
but then I added an actual sprite.
And it has to be a sprite if you
want it to do things interactively.
The lamppost-- not a sprite.
It's just an image a costume,
if you will, for the whole
stage itself, a backdrop.
But this thing is indeed
a sprite because it
needs to respond to code and
events, like dragging and dropping.
So what might I have done
early on with that code?
Well, maybe the first
version would have been
something like this, whereby my
very first version of Oscartime
might have said
something like, oh, this.
How about, let me control the program
as before-- or, rather, events.
When the Green Flag is
clicked, what do I want to do?
Well, I want to go ahead and
forever do something like this.
Forever-- so I want the lid
to open up if I touch it.
So if the cursor gets near the
lid, I want the lid to open up.
And then if I move away,
I want it to close.
So how can I do that?
I want an If, but I just don't want
one question, I really want two,
a fork in the road that goes
left or right, so to speak.
And let me grab this puzzle
piece here, as I did long ago.
So notice, it grows to fill.
What's the question I want to ask?
Well, under Sensing, I'm
going to go ahead here
and say If this trashcan is
Touching the Mouse Pointer--
what do I want to do?
Well, I want to change what
the trashcan looks like.
And this part, I did
in advance of class.
If you go up here to Costumes, this is
where all the graphical stuff happens.
And you'll see that I imported a
whole bunch of different costumes
that effectively, much like a
video, when you play them quickly,
creates the illusion of
movement, some animation.
But it's really just
dot, dot, dot, dot, dot--
different images showing on the screen.
Well, some of these costumes
are called like Oscar1, Oscar2.
Oscar1 is closed.
Oscar2 is open.
So let's just deal with those first.
So if I'm touching the mouse pointer,
let me go under-- how about Looks?
And we didn't use this before,
but there's this block,
Switch Costume to Something Else.
I'm going to drag and drop
this inside of the If.
And notice it's a little bit indented.
I'm going to change it
not to Oscar8, but Oscar2.
Otherwise, If Not Touching
the Mouse Pointer--
this is the other direction
in the fork in the road--
let's go ahead and switch the costume
back to what I described as Oscar1.
So let me run this program.
And not much of interest
is happening yet.
But notice, if I move
the cursor up, down--
but how is that working?
It's just changing the costume
that's being overlaid on the sprite.
So it looks like interactivity,
but you are really
just changing the aesthetics.
And we humans are just kind of
assuming, oh, it's opening up.
Well, no, it's just changing a costume.
So here's the difference.
The high-level abstraction--
trashcan opening.
The lower-level implementation
detail-- costume
changing, creating that illusion.
And if I want it to look prettier, I
could just have many other costumes
and go boom, boom, boom, boom, boom
to create more frames per second,
if you will.
So I need to do one other thing.
Maybe if I accidentally
leave the trashcan open,
let me make one change here.
Let me make sure that
the very first thing
I do when the Green Flag is clicked,
is always start with the trashcan
closed because otherwise, you
might accidentally leave it open.
So this gets me into some default state.
So now it's always closed until
I manually hover over it instead.
Well, what might I have done next?
Well, if I wanted to introduce something
like the trash, I need a second sprite.
And here, in advance, I
grabbed the image already.
Let me pretend that this never happened.
Let me drag this away here.
And now I have nothing in my code
area for this piece of trash.
But it is the second sprite.
And all I did was I clicked on
the little cat plus icon here,
created a second sprite.
I named it trash.
I added a costume for it.
Sort of the aesthetic
stuff, I did in advance.
But here I'll do now the code.
How do I want to do this?
Well, how about when the Green
Flag is clicked, for the trash can,
I want the trash can in parallel to do--
I want the trash, the piece
of trash, to do its own thing.
So what I want it to do is maybe
let's do Motion, how about?
And let's go to a specific coordinate.
Now, there's a lot of options here.
There's Turning, Go to a Random
Position, Go to x,y, Glide,
more elegantly.
There's a lot of different
ways to implement movement.
I just want it to go to a
very specific location first.
So I'm just going to go to x,y first.
And I'm going to say
x, how about, will be--
let's not hardcode this.
Let's just have it be-- well, let's
do it at 0, initially, and then 240.
So-- whoops-- let's do 0,240
so that this piece of trash
always starts at the top
middle of the screen.
If you think back to that coordinate
system, 0,0 is in the middle.
240 is straight above it.
All right, now, after I do
that, what do I want to do?
Well, how about I control
this thing by forever falling.
Now, how do I make the trash move?
We haven't seen this puzzle piece yet.
But under Motion, the very first thing
is called Move Some Number of Steps.
By default, it's 10.
But we'll do it more simply.
Let me go ahead and move--
oh, sorry.
Move is going to move it in
whatever direction it's facing.
I only want it to move down.
So here, even I'm getting confused
as to how many different ways there
are to do things.
What I thing I want to do is this.
Let me only change my y-axis as follows.
So here's another puzzle
piece called Change y.
So again, y is the vertical.
So let me just change
y by one pixel downward
at a time, so -1 one pixel at a time.
So it's kind of slow.
And I think now--
I think that's it.
Let me hit Stop.
Notice that my trashcan is
still going to be interactive.
I haven't changed or deleted that code.
I've just added now code
for my piece of trash.
If I click the Green Flag, notice that--
after I enable it-- let
me start that again.
I had it hidden for before class.
But let me enable it now--
Green Flag, notice it starts dead
center, at x equals 0, y equals 240,
and it's dropping one pixel at a time.
If that seems a little boring, we
can change it to -10 pixels at a time
and, boom, it's done.
So that's how you might
change the speed of a program.
But I'm going to leave
it more simply as -1.
And honestly, it would be nice if it
doesn't always start from the top.
Otherwise, this game is not
going to be very interactive.
I'm literally going to be grabbing the
trash from the same place every time.
So why don't I, instead, Stop this.
Let me go under Operators, and
let's pick a random number.
So let me change the hardcoded--
the manually inputted-- 0, and
let's make x be somewhere between 0,
so in the middle and
all the way over to--
what was it-- oh, I
got my numbers wrong--
240 and my y will be 180.
Sorry, I got my x and my y confused.
So let me play this again.
And now we have a game
that's more like games
you might have played
growing up or even now,
like there's some randomness to it.
So the CPU, so to speak, is
doing something more interesting.
Let me run it again.
Now it's a little to the left.
Now it's a little more to the left.
Again-- now it's back to the right.
So randomness just makes
games more interesting.
And this is why when you play any
video game, if different things are
happening, there's probably
just some randomness.
And it's quantized as
just a simple number.
Now, I think I just need one
final flourish here, if I may.
Let me go ahead and add this.
How about Events-- or rather--
yes, Events.
When Green Flag is clicked, I can do
multiple things within the same sprite.
They don't all have to be
attached to the same one.
Let me go ahead and forever go
ahead and do something else.
How about, Whenever the Trash is--
how about-- Touching the Trash Can--
so Forever If-- let's see,
I need a Sensing block.
So how about, Is Touching--
not the Mouse Pointer, this time,
but Touching Oscar himself there.
Now let's see what happens.
All right, so let's go ahead
and click the Green Flag.
Now I go down over here and let go.
OK, I kind of want it to
go into the trash can.
How do I make it go into the trash can?
How can we take this high-level
idea, put trash into the trash can,
and make it seem to disappear?
Logically, what could we do?
Yeah--
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: OK, so when it
touches it, let's have it disappear.
So I could hide it.
Or honestly, if the game is
going to be ongoing, like it was,
letting me drop more and
more trash, let me just
have it go ahead and pick
a new random location.
So let me do this.
Let me go ahead and Copy this
puzzle piece up here and Duplicate.
And I don't want the whole thing, sorry.
Let me get rid of this.
Let me just do this.
Let me go back to some
random location at the top.
So now notice what happens.
If I click and drag
on it-- here it goes--
and I let go, it looks like
it's going into the trash can
because it snaps back up
to some random location.
Now, the only thing I'm not doing really
is keeping track of any kind of score.
And it turns out, if I full screen
this, it's not going to be draggable,
by default.
So just as a corner case,
so to speak, something
that you might trip over otherwise,
let me go ahead and under, let's
see, Sensing, it turns out I also
need this for the piece of trash.
There's this way of setting,
in Scratch, a sprite
to be draggable or not draggable.
I need to explicitly
make it draggable so
that when I do full
screen this thing now,
it still remains draggable
and someone like myself
can play it again and again.
Well, how about we supplement
this with one final flourish?
Why don't we keep track
now of the user score?
So how about, when the user
actually drags the piece of trash
to the trash can, let me
go under Variables here,
where, in advance, I've already
made myself a variable called Score.
I could have called it x or y or z or
ABC, but that's not very descriptive.
In programming, you typically give
things a more descriptive English,
or some other language, name.
So I called this one Score.
So how do I want to do this in my Score?
Well, let me go ahead and
initially set this game
score to 0 at the very top
of one of these scripts--
one of these programs up here.
And then any time my
piece of trash is touching
Oscar, let's not just jump to the top,
let's change the score by 1 up here.
So now notice, If Touching Oscar,
Change the Score-- that is,
Add 1 to the Score--
and then Pick a new Random location.
And now Green Flag--
let's do this slowly.
Here it goes.
The trashcan opens.
I let go.
And now notice, at the top left of my
program, notice the score is now 2.
Notice the score, if I do this
again, is about to become 3.
And so here we have
building blocks, literally,
of making this program
better and better and better.
And so, indeed, that's how you generally
approach solving any problem with code,
be it in Scratch or C
or Python or some other.
You take this vision you
might have or some vision
you've been assigned in
a homework assignment
and try to break it down
into these constituent parts
and just pluck off the easy ones first.
Put the lamp post there
first, and at least
feel like you're making some progress.
Then pluck off something
like the trash can, and just
make it do a little thing.
And it doesn't have to be
in some same order here.
I could have done this in
a million different ways.
But figure out what the small
pieces are that, ultimately,
like a few of the problems we've solved
today, assemble into a greater solution
there too.
So that you have now a mental model
for these types of blocks and others,
let's return for a moment to this.
We saw a moment ago that when I
started saying, "Hello, David,"
and nesting those puzzle pieces, we had
a whole different paradigm altogether.
My input for that second version of,
"Hello, world," was to now pass in,
for instance, "What's Your Name?"
into my function, called Ask.
That gave me not a side
effect, but what I called,
again, a return value, called
Answer, by default, in Scratch.
And now notice and recall,
when I had that same output
become the input to my next block, it
looked a little something like this--
Say.
So how does this type of block and
this nesting, this stacking of blocks,
fit into the same mental model?
Well, same idea-- my input for that part
of the story is now taking in not one
input but two--
two arguments-- "hello"
and the answer from before.
The function, in this case,
is that new block called Join.
The output thereof is, "Hello,
David," which itself became--
if we sort of animate this--
the input to my final function,
which indeed was still Say.
And this is only to
say-- no pun intended--
that almost everything that you
do with these puzzle pieces,
be it in the context of
Oscartime or the mole whacking
or even just something
simple like, "Hello, world,"
will ultimately fit into that
relatively simple mental model there.
Now, I thought we'd end by taking a
look at just a couple of final examples.
These ones, too, made by
some of your predecessors.
And for this, I thought we
would not write code together,
but read it instead.
And so allow me to open
up one other example here
that will show us a few
different versions of a program
that a predecessor made.
Give me just a moment here.
And we'll see how we might build up
to something even more interactive.
And in just a moment,
we'll see something
they called Ivy's Hardest Game, focused
here on these particular mechanics.
So here is version 0, so to
speak, of this program, wherein
the goal was to create a game where you
have to get out of some kind of maze.
And you have to get out, in this case,
the Harvard crest from this maze.
Let me go ahead and just
hit Play on this Green Flag
so you can see what the first building
block for this program might have been.
Notice that my hand here is actually
on the Arrow keys on my keyboard.
And it seems that by moving
up, down, left, or right,
this little crest on the screen
responds in exactly that way.
Now, let's hypothesize
for just a moment.
Even though we've not done
anything quite like this before,
how might this code be implemented?
How do you get a sprite,
be it a cat or a crest,
to respond to keys on a keyboard--
might you think intuitively?
Yeah--
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah,
there could be something
sensing what key you're pressing on.
And if you do it again
in forever a loop,
you'll just constantly be
listening for keystrokes.
And this is how, like, every
piece of software nowadays works.
It's constantly waiting
for your phone to be tapped
or something to be typed on the screen.
So let me go ahead and look inside
of this existing program here.
And there's more going on,
but we'll take a quick glance
what's actually going on.
Well, up here at top
left, notice, we just
have Go To x Equals 0 and y Equals 0.
That means put the Harvard crest dead
center in the middle of the stage.
Then we have Forever
two functions that we
made in advance as custom functions--
Listen for Keyboard, Feel for Walls.
So it's doing two things at once.
It's forever listening
for the keyboard-- up,
down, left, right-- and
feeling for the walls,
in the sense that if I
get too far to the left,
I don't want it to keep
moving past that black wall.
And if it moves too far to the right, I
don't want it to blow through that wall
either.
So it's going to do two things
constantly, listening for keyboard
and feeling for walls, so to speak.
And how are those implemented?
Well, this one's a bit long.
But on the left here
is Listen for Keyboard.
So this pink puzzle piece,
Listen for Keyboard,
first checks If the Key Up
Arrow is Pressed, question mark,
Boolean expression in a
conditional, Change y By 1.
That means, move it up 1.
Else If the Key Down Arrow is
Pressed, then Change y by -1,
and similar for Left Arrow,
similar for Right Arrow.
And even though there's not
a loop in this pink function,
there is where I'm using it.
So it's constantly being
asked again and again.
How about feeling for walls?
Well, over here to the right--
it's a little cut off-- but here
you have, If Touching Left Wall,
Change x by 1.
So if you hit the wall, it's too late.
You're kind of blowing
through it already.
So I want to move it back one pixel
so it's no longer touching that wall.
Similarly, if it's touching the right
wall, I want to back it up one pixel
so it's no longer touching that wall.
So it's kind of like bouncing
off ever so slightly so that it
doesn't slip through that actual wall.
And what are those walls?
Well, notice down here, it's just
a simple sprite with a black line
that I've oriented vertically
instead of horizontally.
And that's just so that I can ask
questions of these other two sprites.
Now, that gives me that
form of interactivity.
What more can I now do?
Well, what if we make things a
little more interactive here?
Let me go ahead and see
inside version 1 our second.
And let me propose what's
going to happen here.
Well, how might we add a little
something like Yale into the mix?
Well, what's Yale going to do when I hit
the Green Flag now based on this code?
Any hunches?
Here is the code for my Yale sprite.
Yeah--
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah,
it's kind of going to be
an adversarially by blocking
my path, theoretically,
if I keep writing more code.
So why?
It too goes to the middle of the screen.
It points in direction 90 degrees.
So similarly, there's a
whole degree system as well.
And it forever asks this.
If Touching the Left Wall Or--
notice the green block--
Touching the Right Wall, then
just Turn around 180 Degrees.
And indeed, if you think
this through logically,
that just means you're
bouncing this way and this way
by just flipping yourself around 180
degrees for just this Yale sprite.
So if I go ahead and zoom in on
this and click the Green Flag,
I can still move up and down.
But Yale is just kind of doing
this all day long, back and forth
and back and forth, forever.
Nothing bad happens if
I try to go through it.
But we could add that,
certainly, to the mix.
In fact, let's add one final feature
before we play this particular game.
And let me go ahead and open up the
final version of these building blocks
that adds MIT to the mix.
So here is MIT.
Someone want to explain
what this code does?
And this is what we're doing.
This itself is a skill.
Reading someone else's
code and understanding it
is half of the part of
programming besides writing.
Yeah--
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, it's chasing
down the Harvard logo outline.
So this is apparently
the name of the costume
that this student made,
Harvard logo outline.
And apparently, it goes to
a random position first.
But then it forever points to Harvard.
So no matter where I'm
moving it, up, down, left,
or right, MIT is being a little
more strategic than Yale,
bouncing back and forth like this.
So let's go ahead and play
this one in full screen.
And here we have a Green Flag.
So if I move up, MIT,
rather strategically,
is following me no matter where I go.
All right, so still,
nothing bad happens.
But now it's struggling, right?
It's going up, down, up, down.
It's trying to follow me
even though I'm not moving.
So we need some final flourishes.
And so I think, for this, we
need perhaps one final volunteer.
After this, cake awaits
for everyone outside,
as is an end of first
lecture CS50 tradition.
Would you like to come
up and be our volunteer?
[APPLAUSE]
All right.
And so this will be the actual version
but written by one of your predecessors
that I'll full screen here.
It's going to stitch together all
of these same primitives and more,
but add the notion of scores and
lives so that there's actually
a goal, which in this case is to move
the Harvard crest to constantly pursue
the character on the right-hand side
so that your sprite touches that one.
Would you like to introduce yourself?
AUDIENCE: Hi, my name is Mohammed.
DAVID J. MALAN: All right, wonderful.
Welcome aboard.
And here we come with some
instructions and final
flourish if we want to keep the lights
up but perhaps increase the music.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
[MUSIC - MC HAMMER, "U CAN'T TOUCH
THIS"]
MC HAMMER: (SINGING) You can't this.
You can't touch this.
DAVID J. MALAN: Notice he is
using the up, down, left, right.
But there's many more walls now.
First level's pretty easy.
But now Yale's in the mix,
bouncing back and forth.
Again, pretty easy.
Now there's two Yale's at
slightly different positions.
MIT is coming soon.
But first, we have three Yales.
MC HAMMER: (SINGING) As such.
And this is a beat, uh, you can't touch.
DAVID J. MALAN: Very nice.
[APPLAUSE]
MC HAMMER: (SINGING) I told you,
homeboy, you can't touch this.
Yeah, that's how it look when
you know you can't touch this.
Look at my eyes, man,
you can't touch this.
Yo, let me bust the funky
lyrics. you can't touch this.
Fresh new kicks and pants,
you got to like that.
Now, you know you want to dance.
So move out of your seat and get a fly--
DAVID J. MALAN: You got to go quick.
MC HAMMER: (SINGING) Catch
this beat while it's rolling.
Hold on.
Pump a little bit, and let them know
what's going on, like that, like that.
Cold on a mission, so fall on back.
Let them know that you're too much
and this a beat, uh, they can't touch.
Yo, I told you.
You can't touch this.
[APPLAUSE]
Yo, sound the bell.
School's in, sucker.
You can't touch this.
Give me a song, a rhythm.
Making them sweat, that's
what I'm giving them.
Now they know, you
talk about the Hammer,
you talking about a show
that's hyped and tight.
Singers are sweating, so pass
them a wipe or a tape to learn.
What's it going to take--
DAVID J. MALAN: Second-to-last level.
MC HAMMER: (SINGING) Legit.
Either work hard or
you might as well quit.
That's word because you know--
DAVID J. MALAN: Last level.
MC HAMMER: (SINGING)
You can't touch this.
DAVID J. MALAN: Hey!
[LAUGHS]
[APPLAUSE]
Congrats.
All right, that's it for CS50.
Welcome.
Cake is now served.
We'll see you next time.
[PROJECTOR CLICKING]
[MUSIC PLAYING]